A Guide to the Virginia War History Commission, 1915-1931
Library of Virginia
- Series XI: Office Files, 1917-1927
  - Subseries H: Publications
    - (Source Volume 4) Virginia War Agencies, Selective Service and Volunteers
      - "History of the First Virginia Council of Defense" and "History of the Second Virginia Council of Defense" (final revised copy from printer) (Box 241, Folder 4)
      - Personnel Lists for First Virginia Council of Defense, Agricultural Council of Safety, Industrial Council of Safety and Second Virginia Council of Defense (Box 241, Folder 5)
      - "History of the Federal Food Administration in Virginia" (draft) (Box 241, Folder 6)
      - "Historical Sketch of the Federal Food Administration for Virginia" (unpublished manuscript by Hugh B. Sproul, Federal Food Administrator for Virginia) (Box 241, Folder 7)
      - "History of the Work of the Federal Food Administrator in Virginia" (unpublished manuscript by J.T. Bethel) (Box 241, Folder 8)
      - "History of the Federal Fuel Administration in Virginia" (draft) (part one) (Box 242, Folder 1)
      - "History of the Federal Fuel Administration in Virginia" (draft) (part two) (Box 242, Folder 2)
      - "Historical Sketch of Agriculture in Virginia before 1914" (unpublished manuscript) (Box 242, Folder 3)
      - "The Selective Service Act in Virginia" (Draft) (Box 242, Folder 4)
      - "The Selective Service Act in Virginia" (unpublished manuscripts) (Box 242, Folder 5)
      - Galleys for Chapters on Federal Food Administration and Federal Fuel Administration in Virginia (Box 242, Folder 6)
      - Galleys for Chapter on Second Virginia Council of Defense (Box 242, Folder 7)
      - Index to Source Material of First and Second Councils of Defense in Virginia (Draft) (Box 242, Folder 8)
      - Index to Source Material - Agricultural Council of Safety (Draft) (Box 242, Folder 9)
    - (Source Volume 5) Virginia Military Organizations in the World War
      - Forward (Draft - with handwritten corrections by Arthur Kyle Davis) (Box 242, Folder 10)
      - Forward (Draft - as originally dictated) (Box 242, Folder 11)
      - Forward (Draft - revised copy) (Box 242, Folder 12)
      - Stories of Virginia Military Units-Duplicates (Drafts) (Box 242, Folder 13)
      - Rosters of Virginia Military Units-Duplicates (Drafts) (Box 243, Folder 1)
      - "History of the Virginia State Volunteers" (Draft) (Box 243, Folder 2)
      - Muster Rolls of the Virginia State Volunteers, 1917-1920 (Draft) (Box 243, Folder 3)
      - "History of the Home Guard Organizations in Virginia" (Draft) (Box 243, Folder 4)
      - Personnel of Virginia Home Guard (Draft) (Box 243, Folder 5)
    - (Source Volume 6) Virginia Communities in War Time
      - Forward (Draft) (Box 243, Folder 6)
    - (Source Volume 7) Virginia Communities in War Time
      - Forward and Index Page (Draft) (Box 243, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Unidentified Handwritten Manuscript(s) (incomplete) (Box 243, Folder 8)
      - Draft of Outline for Research by Local Branches (incomplete) (Box 243, Folder 9)
      - Duplicate Copies of Commission Publications (Box 244)
      - Duplicate Copies of Commission Publications (Box 245)
- Series XII: First Virginia Council of Defense, 1917-1918
  The Council of National Defense was created by an act of Congress on 29 August 1916 to coordinate all national resources pertaining to the efficient mobilization and maintenance of the United States armed forces. After the United States declared war on Germany in April 1917, the federal government requested that each state create a State Council of Defense to carry out the duties of the National Council. To comply with this request, Virginia Governor Henry Carter Stuart created an unwieldy organization which included the Agricultural Council of Safety (18 April 1917), Industrial Council of Safety (25 April 1917), and the Virginia Council of Defense (26 April 1917). The duties of each council overlapped but each retained its own identity. The Virginia Council of Defense was essentially an advisory body which coordinated the work of all councils. Governor Westmoreland Davis corrected this situation when he abolished all three councils in February 1918 and organized all defense activities under the Second Virginia Council of Defense. Members of the First Virginia Council of Defense included: General Edward W. Nichols, Superintendent of the Virginia Military Institute; L.E. Johnson, President of the Norfolk and Western Railway Company; R. Walton Moore, United States Representative; Homer L. Ferguson, President of the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company; Colonel Elijah B. White; Rev. Collins Denny; Dr. Ennion G. Williams, State Health Commissioner; James O. Winston; Richard Evelyn Byrd; D. Lawrence Groner; George B. Keezell; John H. Crockett; Jesse M. Jones; and A.P. Walker.
  The Virginia War History Commission published a history of the First Virginia Council of Defense and an index to their records in Virginia War Agencies, Selective Services and Volunteers (Source Volume 4) (Richmond: 1926, pp. 3-34 & 395-418), edited by Arthur Kyle Davis.
  The First Virginia Council of Defense series is housed in 6 boxes and one oversized folder and is arranged in two(2) subseries. Subseries have been designated for Source Material and Records. The series consists primarily of incoming and outgoing correspondence to the Council particularly Executive Secretary Colonel William M. Hunley, Speakers' Bureau head Lewis H. Machen and Virginia Governor Henry Stuart, and copies of publications, pamphlets and newsletters from the Council of National Defense and from other state councils. It is unknown why some of the records the Virginia Council were filed with Source Materials (Subseries A) and other similar records with Records (Subseries B). Researchers should check both subseries. These records document the activities of the First Virginia Council of Defense in Virginia including such areas as agriculture, food conservation, military matters, publicity, religious forces, Speakers' Bureau, and the Woman's Division.
  The Source Material subseries is housed in 5 boxes and is indexed in Virginia War Agencies, Selective Services and Volunteers (Source Volume 4) (Richmond: 1926, pp. 395-418), edited by Arthur Kyle Davis. The records in this subseries are arranged by topic and sub-heading. Topics include agriculture, farmers, food conservation, fuel conservation, health and morals, industry and labor, Liberty Loans, local councils, military matters, miscellaneous activities of Council, other states, publicity, religious forces, Speakers' Bureau, transportation, Woman's Division and closing period of Council. When this series was originally processed in 2003, not all of the indexed records were extant. Most of the missing records were located in 2005 and have been added to the collection. Unfortunately, very few records are extant for the Woman's Division.
  Records filed under Agriculture include correspondence related to the Boys' Working Reserve and Boy Scouts as aids to farmers, exemption for farm laborers from military service, loans to farmers and offers of land to the government.
  The Food Conservation files list bakers who promise to co-operate with Council in the campaign against acceptance of unsold bread and exemptions from military service sought by ice manufacturers. Harry F. Byrd's appointment as Virginia Fuel Administrator is highlighted in correspondence under Fuel Conservation. Military Matters described the formation of Home Guards, recruiting and training camp activities.
  The Speakers' Bureau correspondence contain replies to letters and telegrams of Lewis H. Machen, dated 25 May 1917 requesting cooperation in the June 1917 speaking campaign and the speaking campaign in the fall of 1917. Additional records include materials submitted by Council's of Defense of other states.
  The Records subseries is housed in 1 box and one oversized folder. This material is not indexed. Records of note include the minutes of the Council of Defense for 1917 and 1918. An oversized scrapbook contains newspaper clippings (Richmond Times-Dispatch and Richmond News-Leader) of the Council's activities from May 1917 to January 1918.
  - Other States - Missouri (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 246, Folder 1)
  - Other States - Montana (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 246, Folder 2)
  - Other States - Nevada (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 246, Folder 3)
  - Other States - New Hampshire (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 246, Folder 4)
  - Other States - New Jersey (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 246, Folder 5)
  - Other States - New Mexico (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 246, Folder 6)
  - Source Material - Speakers' Bureau (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 246, Folder 7)
  - Source Material - Speakers' Bureau, Speaking Campaign, Fall of 1917 (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 246, Folder 8)
  - Source Material - Woman's Division (Original Box 8, Folder 16) (Box 246, Folder 9)
  - Source Material - Closing Period of Council (Original Box 8, Folder 17) (Box 246, Folder 10)
  - Records - Not Indexed (Box 246, Folder 11)
  - Records - Not Indexed (Box 246, Folder 12)
  - Records - Not Indexed (Box 246, Folder 13)
  - Records - Miscellaneous (Box 246, Folder 14)
  - Minutes of Virginia Council of Defense, 1917-1918 (Box 247, Folder 1)
  - Transcript of Proceedings of National Defense Conference, 2-3 May 1917 (Box 247, Folder 2)
  - Draft of Index of Source Material of the First Virginia Council of Defense (typed) (Box 247, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified Index (possibly references to newspaper clippings) (Box 247, Folder 4)
  - Organization Period (Original Box 1, Folder 1) (Box 247a, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture (Original Box 1, Folder 2) (Box 247a, Folder 2)
  - Food Conservation (Original Box 1, Folder 3) (Box 247a, Folder 3)
  - Fuel Conservation (Original Box 2, Folder 4) (Box 247a, Folder 4)
  - Health and Morals (Original Box 2, Folder 5) (Box 247a, Folder 5)
  - Industry and Labor (Original Box 2, Folder 6) (Box 247a, Folder 6)
  - Liberty Loans (Original Box 2, Folder 7) (Box 247a, Folder 7)
  - Local Councils (Original Box 2, Folder 8) (Box 247a, Folder 8)
  - Military Matters (Original Box 2, Folder 9) (Box 247a, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Activities of Council (Original Box 3, Folder 10) (Box 247a, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Activities of Council (Original Box 3, Folder 10) (Box 247b, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Activities of Council (Original Box 3, Folder 10) (Box 247b, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Activities of Council, Bills and Receipts (Original Box 3, Folder 10) (Box 247b, Folder 3)
  - Other States, Alabama-Illinois (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 247b, Folder 4)
  - Other States, Indiana-Mississippi (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 247b, Folder 5)
  - Other States, Missouri-Ohio (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 247b, Folder 6)
  - Other States, Oklahoma-Wyoming (Original Box 4, Folder 11) (Box 247b, Folder 7)
  - Publicity, National Council Correspondence (Original Box 5, Folder 12) (Box 247c, Folder 1)
  - Publicity, Local Publicity (Original Box 5, Folder 12) (Box 247c, Folder 2)
  - Religious Forces (Original Box 5, Folder 13) (Box 247c, Folder 3)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Letters Promising Cooperation in Counties, Accomack County - Goochland County (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247c, Folder 4)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Letters Promising Cooperation in Counties, Grayson County - Smyth County (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247c, Folder 5)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Letters Promising Cooperation in Counties, Southampton County - Wythe County (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247c, Folder 6)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Letters Promising Cooperation in Cities, Alexandria - Williamsburg (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247c, Folder 7)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Telegrams Promising Cooperation in Counties, Accomack County - Wise County (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247d, Folder 1)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Telegrams Promising Cooperation in Cities, Alexandria - Williamsburg (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247d, Folder 2)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Letters Giving Reasons for Inability to Cooperate in Campaign in Counties, Alleghany County - Warren County (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247d, Folder 3)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Letters Giving Reasons for Inability to Cooperate in Campaign in Cities, Alexandria - Winchester (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247d, Folder 4)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Telegrams Giving Reasons for Inability to Speak in Cities and Counties (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247d, Folder 5)
  - Speakers' Bureau, Replies of Louis H. Machen to Telegrams and Letters Listed Above (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247d, Folder 6)
  - Speakers' Bureau (Original Box 6, Folder 14) (Box 247d, Folder 7)
  - Transportation (Original Box 7, Folder 15) (Box 247d, Folder 8)
  - Woman's Division, Organization of Woman's Committee (Original Box 8, Folder 16) (Box 247d, Folder 9)
- Series XIII: Virginia Agricultural Council of Safety, 1917-1918
  The Council of National Defense was created by an act of Congress on 29 August 1916 to coordinate all national resources pertaining to the efficient mobilization and maintenance of the United States armed forces. After the United States declared war on Germany in April 1917, the federal government requested that each state create a State Council of Defense to carry out the duties of the National Council. To comply with this request, Virginia Governor Henry Carter Stuart created an unwieldy organization which included the Agricultural Council of Safety (18 April 1917), Industrial Council of Safety (25 April 1917), and the Virginia Council of Defense (26 April 1917). The duties of each council overlapped but each retained its own identity. The Virginia Council of Defense was essentially an advisory body which coordinated the work of all councils. Governor Westmoreland Davis corrected this situation when he abolished all three councils in February 1918 and organized all defense activities under the Second Virginia Council of Defense. The Agricultural Council of Safety focused on food production and conservation. Members of the Executive Council were: Chairman Dr. Jesse M. Jones of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and Secretary B.C. Moomaw, Jr. Other members of the Council included T.O. Sandy, V. Vaden, Ella G. Agnew, Mrs. B.B. Munford, Dr. H.B. Frissell, B.M. Shepherd, Dr. R.C. Stearns, Dr. J.D. Eggleston, A.B. Thornhill and B.F. Purcell. Council Secretary B.C. Moomaw established a central office in Richmond and the Council appointed local councils for each county to carry out its' work.
  The Virginia Agricultural Council of Safety series is housed in 5 boxes. The Virginia War History Commission published a history of the Virginia Agricultural Council of Safety and an index to their records in Virginia War Agencies, Selective Services and Volunteers (Source Volume 4) (Richmond: 1926, pp. 27-32 & 457-480), edited by Arthur Kyle Davis. The folder numbering for this series corresponds to the numbering used in the index; records not indexed follow. Not all indexed records are extant. The majority of the material consists primarily of correspondence between Council Chairman Jesse M. Jones and Secretary B.C. Moomaw and the local councils outlining their organization (including a list of members), plans, and activities. Other subjects include assistance offered by the Boy Scouts, Farm Labor Exemptions, Food Production and Conservation, Negro Agricultural Councils, Women's Work and correspondence to Jesse M. Jones. Miscellaneous records include lists of local council members and drafts of the index to the Council's records.
  - Accomack County (Box 248, Folder 1)
  - Albemarle County (Box 248, Folder 2)
  - Alexandria County (Box 248, Folder 3)
  - Alleghany County (Box 248, Folder 4)
  - Amelia County (Box 248, Folder 5)
  - Amherst County (Box 248, Folder 6)
  - Appomattox County (Box 248, Folder 7)
  - Augusta County (Box 248, Folder 8)
  - Bath County (Box 248, Folder 9)
  - Bedford County (Box 248, Folder 10)
  - Botetourt County (Box 248, Folder 11)
  - Brunswick County (Box 248, Folder 12)
  - Buchanan County (Box 248, Folder 13)
  - Buckingham County (Box 248, Folder 13a)
  - Campbell County (Box 248, Folder 14)
  - Caroline County (Box 248, Folder 15)
  - Carroll County (Box 248, Folder 16)
  - Charles City County (Box 248, Folder 17)
  - Charlotte County (Box 248, Folder 18)
  - Chesterfield County (Box 248, Folder 19)
  - Clarke County (Box 248, Folder 20)
  - Craig County (Box 248, Folder 21)
  - Culpeper County (Box 248, Folder 22)
  - Cumberland County (Box 248, Folder 23)
  - Dickenson County (Box 248, Folder 24)
  - Dinwiddie County (Box 248, Folder 25)
  - Elizabeth City County (Box 248, Folder 26)
  - Essex County (Box 248, Folder 27)
  - Fairfax County (Box 248, Folder 28)
  - Fauquier County (Box 248, Folder 29)
  - Floyd County (Box 248, Folder 30)
  - Fluvanna County (Box 248, Folder 31)
  - Franklin County (Box 248, Folder 32)
  - Frederick County (Box 248, Folder 33)
  - Gloucester County (Box 248, Folder 33a)
  - Goochland County (Box 248, Folder 34)
  - Giles County (Box 248, Folder 35)
  - Grayson County (Box 248, Folder 36)
  - Greene County (Box 248, Folder 37)
  - Greensville County (Box 248, Folder 38)
  - Halifax County (Box 248, Folder 39)
  - Hanover County (Box 248, Folder 40)
  - Henrico County (Box 248, Folder 41)
  - Henry County (Box 248, Folder 41a)
  - Highland County (Box 248, Folder 42)
  - James City County (Box 248, Folder 43)
  - King and Queen County (Box 248, Folder 44)
  - King George County (Box 248, Folder 45)
  - Lancaster County (Box 248, Folder 46)
  - Lee County (Box 248, Folder 47)
  - Isle of Wight County (Box 248, Folder 48)
  - Loudoun County (Box 248, Folder 49)
  - Louisa County (Box 249, Folder 50)
  - Lunenburg County (Box 249, Folder 51)
  - Madison County (Box 249, Folder 52)
  - Mathews County (Box 249, Folder 53)
  - Mecklenburg County (Box 249, Folder 54)
  - Middlesex County (Box 249, Folder 55)
  - Montgomery County (Box 249, Folder 56)
  - Nansemond County (Box 249, Folder 56a)
  - Nelson County (Box 249, Folder 57)
  - New Kent County (Box 249, Folder 58)
  - Norfolk County (Box 249, Folder 59)
  - Northampton County (Box 249, Folder 60)
  - Northumberland County (Box 249, Folder 61)
  - Nottoway County (Box 249, Folder 62)
  - Orange County (Box 249, Folder 63)
  - Page County (Box 249, Folder 64)
  - Patrick County (Box 249, Folder 64a)
  - Pittsylvania County (Box 249, Folder 65)
  - Powhatan County (Box 249, Folder 66)
  - Prince Edward County (Box 249, Folder 67)
  - Prince William County (Box 249, Folder 68)
  - Prince George County (Box 249, Folder 69)
  - Princess Anne County (Box 249, Folder 70)
  - Pulaski County (Box 249, Folder 71)
  - Rappahannock County (Box 249, Folder 72)
  - Richmond County (Box 249, Folder 73)
  - Roanoke County (Box 249, Folder 74)
  - Rockbridge County (Box 249, Folder 75)
  - Rockingham County (Box 249, Folder 76)
  - Russell County (Box 249, Folder 77)
  - Scott County (Box 249, Folder 78)
  - Shenandoah County (Box 249, Folder 79)
  - Southampton County (Box 249, Folder 80)
  - Smyth County (Box 249, Folder 81)
  - Spotsylvania County (Box 249, Folder 82)
  - Stafford County (Box 249, Folder 83)
  - Surry County (Box 249, Folder 84)
  - Sussex County (Box 249, Folder 85)
  - Tazewell County (Box 249, Folder 86)
  - Warwick County (Box 249, Folder 87)
  - Washington County (Box 249, Folder 88)
  - Westmoreland County (Box 249, Folder 89)
  - Wise County (Box 249, Folder 90)
  - Wythe County (Box 249, Folder 91)
  - York County (Box 249, Folder 92)
  - Boy Scouts and Offers of Aid to Council (Box 250, Folder 93)
  - Farm Labor Exemptions (Box 250, Folder 94)
  - Finances of Council (Box 250, Folder 95)
  - Food Production and Conservation (Box 250, Folder 96)
  - Form Letters not included elsewhere in this Index (Box 250, Folder 97)
  - Labor (Box 250, Folder 98)
  - Loans to Farmers (Box 250, Folder 99)
  - Local Councils (Box 250, Folder 100)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 250, Folder 101)
  - Negro Agricultural Councils (Box 250, Folder 102)
  - Offers of Service and of Land to State or National Government (Box 250, Folder 103)
  - Price Regulation (Box 250, Folder 104)
  - Women's Work (Box 250, Folder 105)
  - Jones, Jesse M. (Box 251, Folder 1)
  - Index by County (Box 251, Folder 2)
  - List of Personnel, Local Councils (Box 251, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous - Unidentified (Box 251, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous - Unidentified (Box 251, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous - Unidentified (Box 251, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous - Unidentified (Box 251, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous - Unidentified (Box 251, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous - Report of County Agricultural Councils of Safety in the Organized Counties of the State (Box 252, Folder 1)
  - Index to Correspondence by Locality (Box 252, Folder 2)
  - Index to Correspondence by Locality (duplicate) (Box 252, Folder 3)
  - List of Personnel, Local Councils (duplicate, incomplete) (Box 252, Folder 4)
  - List of Personnel, Local Councils (duplicate, incomplete) (Box 252, Folder 5)
  - Handwritten drafts of Index to Agricultural Council of Safety Records; and typed drafts of narrative (Box 252, Folder 6)
- Series XIV: Second Virginia Council of Defense, 1917-1921, 1923-1924
  The Council of National Defense was created by an act of Congress on 29 August 1916 to coordinate all national resources pertaining to the efficient mobilization and maintenance of the United States armed forces. After the United States declared war on Germany in April 1917, the federal government requested that each state create a State Council of Defense to carry out the duties of the National Council. To comply with this request, Virginia Governor Henry Carter Stuart created an unwieldy organization which included the Agricultural Council of Safety (18 April 1917), Industrial Council of Safety (25 April 1917), and the Virginia Council of Defense (26 April 1917). The duties of each council overlapped but each retained its own identity. The Virginia Council of Defense was essentially an advisory body which coordinated the work of all councils. Governor Westmoreland Davis corrected this situation when he abolished all three councils in February 1918 and organized all defense activities under the Second Virginia Council of Defense.
  The purpose of the Second Virginia Council of Defense remained the same: "to co-ordinate and to unify the work of all government departments and civic, relief and philanthropic organizations to the end of an efficient and successful execution of war demands in the State of Virginia." The Second Council created local councils to carry out policy. The Council was involved in a variety of economic and national defense activities including: highways and transportation, housing, industries, food conservation, agriculture, livestock, labor, health, National Council of Defense, and publicity campaigns. Unlike the first council, the Second Virginia Council of Defense had statutory backing, its' members consisted primarily of state government officials who were already engaged in carrying out war-time activities, and it hired a full-time Executive Secretary to execute Council policy. A complete history of the Second Virginia Council of Defense can be found in Virginia War Agencies, Selective Services and Volunteers (Source Volume 4) (Richmond: 1926, pp. 35-176), edited by Arthur Kyle Davis.